<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="v3dcsg2html.xsl"?>
<guidelines> 
<!--	xmlns="http://www.sechsta-sinn.de/velox" 
	xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
	xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.sechsta-sinn.de/velox csg.xsd" -->
	<title>Velox3D Coding Conventions</title>
	<subtitle>Naming conventions and recommendes practices</subtitle>
	<author>Jan Rehders, Christian Nowke</author>
	<version>009</version>

	<section name="Naming">
		<rule>
			Namespaces have short lower case letter names without underscored like 'v3d', 'graphics' etc
		</rule>
		<rule>
			All velox identifiers have to be inside the v3d namespace or one of it's childs.
		</rule>
		<rule>
			Identifiers should be self describing. Their name should indicate their primary purpose. Do not use idetifiers
			which might be misleading. Only use abbreviations where it their meaning can be clearly seen even by people not
			familar with the system
		</rule>
		<rule>
			All velox class, struct, enum and function names start with upper case letters. Use an upper case for each
			'sub word' inside the identifier. Example: <br/>
			<code>
class VEditorSuite;
void PrintSomeLine();
			</code>
		</rule>
		<rule>
			All velox classes, structs and enums which are not nested inside another class have to be prefixed with an 
			upper case 'V'. Interface classes are prefixed with 'IV'. Nested types don't have a prefix. <br/>
			Examples:
			<code>
class VTopLevel
{
  enum NestedEnum { One, Two };
  class NestedClass;
  struct NestedStruct;
};

struct IVSomeInterface
{
	typedef void* EvilPtr;
};

enum VTopLevelEnum
{
	One, Two
};
			</code>
		</rule>
		<rule>
			enum member names start with an uppercase letter, each 'subword' starts with an upper case letter
			<code>
enum VSomeEnum
{
	FirstValue, 
	SecondValue
};
			</code>
		</rule>
		<rule>
			Variables which are class members have an additional prefix "m_", global variables have the prefix "g_" and 
			static variables are prefixed with "s_". Use in_, out_ and io_ prefixes for function parameters, and simple type 
			prefixes when sensible. Local variables only get type prefixes. When no prefix makes sence (instances of a class 
			etc) make the first word lower case (vertexColor) to be distinguished from a typename.
			Use prefixes for types based on their semantics not on their type (n for number instead of dw for DWORD etc)
			<code>
vint m_nNumber;
vchar m_cWhatever;
static vushort gs_nFoo;
std::string m_strName;
FILE* m_pFile;
vfloat32 m_fValue;
vfloat64 m_fValue;
vulong m_nValue;
vlong m_nValue;
			</code>			
			<reason>
				The variable name now shows the scope of the variable, this is especially good for programmers who did not work 
				on the code previously.
			</reason>
		</rule>
	</section>
	
	<section name="Style">
		<rule>
			Use the template files located at velox/Workspace/Templates for orientation how to structure velox header,
			implementation and inline files
		</rule>
		<rule>
			Do not use the C++ standard types. Instead use the velox typedef versions. (vint instead of int, etc)
			<reason>Historical nonsense passed into habit ;)</reason>
		</rule>
		<rule>
			Only use system dependent typed like DWORD, HWND etc where absolutely required (= system dependent code)
		</rule>
		<rule>
			Each class declaration has to be commented in a way readable by doxygen. (Javadoc style preferred)
		</rule>
		<rule>
			Comment everything. Document enough that anyone without any knowledge about the system will be able to use it
			after reading your documentation. Name your identifiers in a self describing way showing their primary intent.
			Use comments where necessary to understand your code. Remember that other people might have trouble following
			train of thoughs which where obvious to you while coding them. 
		</rule>
		<rule>
			Prefer speaking identifiers over javadoc annotations over a seperate documentation but do not skip anyone of 
			them when they are necessary for understanding.
		</rule>
		<rule type="recommended">
			Namespace declarations should have the following form:
			<code>
--------------------------------------------------------------------------------
namespace v3d {
namespace blub {
--------------------------------------------------------------------------------

class NoIndentingForNamespace;

--------------------------------------------------------------------------------
} // namespace blub
} // namespace v3d
--------------------------------------------------------------------------------
      </code>
			or
      <code>
--------------------------------------------------------------------------------
namespace v3d { namespace blub {
--------------------------------------------------------------------------------

class NoIndentingForNamespace;

--------------------------------------------------------------------------------
}} // namspace v3d::blub
--------------------------------------------------------------------------------
      </code>      
		</rule>
		<rule>
			Never specifiy public member data inside a class. Use access functions (inline if performance is critical)
			instead.
			<reason>
				If this rule is applied then the internal data storage of a class can still be changed without modifying 
				the interface. Giving direct access to member variables forbids you to change any variable in the class in 
				the future.
			</reason>
		</rule>
		<rule>
			Do not implement functions in a header. If they need to be inline put them inside a seperate .inl file which
			will be included by the header
			<reason>
				Reading code will be easier. When using inline member functions, put them into a seperate .inl file.
			</reason>
		</rule>
		<rule>
			A member function that does not affect the state of an object has to be declared as const
			<code>
			vbool VClass::GetSomething() const
			{
      		return m_bSomething;
			}
			</code>
			<reason>
				Only const functions are accessible when having a const-pointer to an object
			</reason>
		</rule>
		
		<rule>
			Use const for reference and pointer function parameters in case they don't get modified
			<code>
void Print(const std::string&amp; message);
void Clear(std::string&amp; message);
//...
const std::string msg("i can only be passed to Print");
			</code>
			<reason>
				The function's client should know when he can trust a parameter not being modified. Const variables could not
				be passed when a non const reference is expected
			</reason>
		</rule>
	</section>
	
	<section name="Files">
		<rule>
			The filename has to be identical with the name of the class which is implemented in it. Use correct case
			<reason>
				The filename for a class is then obvious, even for programmers who didnt work on the project
				previously
			</reason>
		</rule>
		<rule>
			Header files are called *.h, Implementation files *.cpp and inline files *.inl
		</rule>
		<rule>
			Only one class should be implemented per file.
			<reason>
				This makes compile times shorter usually and simplifies finding the implementation / declaration of a 
				specific class.
			</reason>
		</rule>
		<rule>
			Neither use dependent characters nor spaces in the filenames.
			<reason>Not all plattforms support these.</reason>
		</rule>
		<rule>
			Try not to include any other header files
			<reason>This helps to avoid cyclic dependencies and decreases compile times.</reason>
		</rule>
		<rule>
			Include files have to be guarded against multiple inclusion using a macro named V3D_FILENAME_YYYY_MM_DD_H.
			YYYY_MM_DD means the date of creation, FileName the file's name in CAPS. Do not use #pragma once etc
			<code>
#ifndef V3D_VSOMEFILE_2004_06_11_H
#define V3D_VSOMEFILE_2004_06_11_H
//...
#endif V3D_VSOMEFILE_2004_06_11_H
			</code>
		</rule>
		<rule>
			Header files which are part of the public API of velox are placed in the velox/API directory. Headers being
			part of a service are placed in velox/API/V3d/.. and headers of the velox .lib are located in
			velox/API/V3dLib/...
			Header files which are part of the implementation and shall not be available for clients of the engine
			are located in the same dir than their corresponding cpp file inside the velox/Source directory
		</rule>
		<rule>
			Do not use anonymous struct in unions
			<code>
// Don't write
union VColor
{
  struct
  {
    vuchar m_ucR;
    vuchar m_ucG;
    vuchar m_ucB;
    vuchar m_ucA;
  };
  DWORD m_dwColor;
}

// Instead use
union VColor
{
  struct AnyName
  {
    vuchar m_ucR;
    vuchar m_ucG;
    vuchar m_ucB;
    vuchar m_ucA;
  };
  DWORD m_dwColor;
}
			</code>
			<reason>This is only supported by Microsoft Visual C++ and GCC 3.0.</reason>
		</rule>
		
	</section>
	
	<section name="CVS usage">
		<rule>
			Always write to your specific textfile in the worklog directory what you are currently doing and what you 
			have finished. Each member of the team uses exectly one file named after his nick or real name
			<reason>
					The rest of the team knows who is working on which part. Apart from this fact, this mechanism helps 
					avoiding multiple people working on the same piece of source code at the same time.
			</reason>
		</rule>
		<rule>
			Only commit code that compiles. Commit code as soon as possible but try not to commit code which you know is 
			very buggy/unstable
		</rule>
	</section>
	
	<section name="Coding practices">
		<rule>
			Always initialize variables with a value
			<reason>
				This will probably decrease the number of bugs by avoiding error caused by uninitialised variables
			</reason>
		</rule>
		<rule>
			Use the "resource aquisition is initialisation" idiom. (see SmartPointer tutorial)
		</rule>
	</section>

<!--

	<br>


	<br>
	<b>Rule</b>: Symbolic constants have to be written in uppercase and have to be prefixed with "V3D_". Avoid #defines whenever possible.<br>
	<b>Reason</b>:	A standard for constant naming has to be defined and it helps to avoid problems with constants from different packages.<br>
	<b>Example</b>:<br>
	#define V3D_USESTL<br>
	const V3D_BUFFERSIZE 16<br>

	<b>Rule</b>: Do not add comments directly after a symbolic constant.<br>
	<b>Reason</b>:	Compilers other than Microsoft Visual C++ might interpret the comment being part of the constant and thus will things will definately not work correctly.<br>
	<b>Example</b>:<br>
	#define V3D_BUFFERSIZE 16 // Not here<br>
	// Better here<br>
	#define V3D_BUFFERSIZE 16<br>

	<br>

	<b>Rule</b>: Always provide empty brackets when deleting memory of an array.<br>
	<b>Reason</b>:	Deleting memory without empty brackets will not free the complete memory.<br>
	<b>Example</b>: vUchar* pFoo = new VUChar[16]; ... delete [] pFoo;<br>

	<br>

	<b>Rule</b>: Always assign 0 to a pointer pointing to deallocated memory. Best use the SafeDelete and SafeDeleteArray functions from v3d/Core/VMemory.h<br>
	<b>Reason</b>: Freeing memory without resetting the pointer is a common reason for a potential crash.<br>
	<b>Example</b>: <br>
	delete [] pFoo; pFoo = NULL; <br>
	// or even better: <br>
	SafeDeleteArray(pFoo); <br>
	<br>

	<br>

	<b>Rule</b>: Never allocate memory somebody else has to deallocate (and other way round).<br>
	<b>Reason</b>:	Allocating memory in package A and deallocating it in B won't work if the packages use different memory models. Apart from this, it will most likely cause memory leaks. Thus such code should never be written.<br>

	<br>

	<b>Rule</b>: Use assertions whenever it might be helpful for bug hunting.<br>

	<br>

	<b>Rule</b>: Never put function calls inside a call of the assertion macro<br>
	<b>Reason</b>:	This function will not be called in release mode.<br>
	<b>Example</b>: V3D_ASSERT(VClass::DoSomething() == true);<br>

	<br>

	<b>Rule</b>: If asserting function results, use the V3D_VERIFY() macro from v3d/Core/VAssert.h <br>
	<b>Reason</b>: Function calls will still be done in release compiles.<br>
	<b>Example</b>: V3D_VERIFY(VClass::DoSomething());<br>

	<br>

	<b>Rule</b>: Opening brackets have to be written in the next line. Same rule applies for closing brackets and other structures where you are opening brackets (like if or while).<br>
	<b>Example</b>:<br>
	// Use<br>
	for (i=0; i<3; i++)<br>
	{<br>
	}<br>
-->
</guidelines>
